Guide to the Filmer Stuart Cuckow Northrop Papers
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
Filmer Stuart Cuckow Northrop papers
1914-1992
1914-1985
MS 627
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
29.5
The papers contain correspondence, notes and lectures, writings, research materials, publications of other scholars, photographs, journals, and miscellanea documenting the professional career of Filmer Stuart Cuckow Northrop, professor of philosophy and law at Yale University from 1923-1962. The papers primarily document the professional activities and research interests of Northrop, not his Yale teaching career and personal life. The correspondence reflects his professional and research interests, in particular such subjects as philosophy of science, philosophy of law, oriental philosophy, and international relations. The papers contain typescripts of three books, notes for courses taken and on conferences attended, research files, and a variety of other material documenting Northrop's professional career.
Northrop, F. S. C. (Filmer Stuart Cuckow), 1893-1992
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Transferred from Yale Law School, 1971; small additions, 1974-1979; received from the Estate of Filmer Stuart Cuckow Northrop, 1993; gift of Norman Riise, 1993; and gift of Robert A. Driscoll, 1997 and 1998.
Related Material
Correspondence of World War II servicemen from Silliman College, Yale University, to the master of the college and his wife, RU 85, Manuscripts and Archives, Yale University Library.
Arrangement
Arranged in five series and four additions: I. Professional Papers. II. Writings. III. Research Material. IV. Writings of others. V. Personal Papers.
Scope and Contents
The Filmer Stuart Cuckow Northrop Papers document many of the activities and professional interests of the well-known Yale Professor of Philosophy and Philosophy and Law. Although the papers span the dates 1914-1979, the bulk of the material covers the years 1940-1972. The major part of the Northrop Papers were transferred to Manuscripts and Archives from the Yale Law School in 1971. Several small additions to the papers were made between 1974 and 1979. Significant related material can be found in YRG 41-A-1 Collection of Yale War Time Letters. In YRG 41-A-1 are a series of letters Christine Johnston Northrop received during World War I, when her husband was Master of Silliman College.
The Northrop Papers are divided into five series, Series I, PROFESSIONAL PAPERS, has two sections: Subject Files and Notes and Lectures.
The Subject Files part of Series I, Boxes 1-8, may be of greatest interest to researchers, for it contains the bulk of the correspondence in the collection. Subject Files have letters that concern his wide ranging philosophical interests; contains reactions to and comments about his many published books and articles, the most thought provoking being The Meeting of East and West (1946); and includes correspondence documenting such professional activities as attendance at major philosophical conferences, membership and participation in professional organizations, and lectures delivered. Given Northrop's international reputation, it is, therefore, not surprising to find letters from scholars in Europe, India, Pakistan, Japan, Australia, Mexico, and other parts of Latin America.
The major subjects covered in the correspondence of this important twentieth century philosopher include the philosophy of science, philosophy of law, Hindu philosophy, oriental philosophy, comparative religion, and United States foreign policy in the post-World War II era.
The second section of Series I, Notes and Lectures, fills Boxes 9-11. There are notes on courses taken by Northrop in graduate school, notes on conferences he attended, notes on books read and conversations with other scholars, and notes on such subjects as Newtonian mechanics, music, and European politics. Lectures make up just over ten percent of the material in this section. Folders 237 and 268 contain class materials and outlines, folders 239-41 and 267 contain class lectures, folders 242 and 269 have material for special lectures, and the section has three folders of lecture abstracts.
Series II, WRITINGS, is also made up of two sections. Part one, Books, Boxes 12-13, has typescripts of The Meeting of East and West, The Logic of the Sciences and Humanities, and Man, Nature and God. The second section, entitled Articles, is housed in Boxes 14-17. In addition to published articles, the section includes some eighteen book reviews written by Northrop, copies of oral presentations, introductions to books written by others, two unpublished manuscripts, and a partial bibliography of Northrop's writings in folder 305. The published articles concern the same subjects found in Subject Files. There are around twenty-five articles on the relationship between philosphy and science, another seventeen on philosophy and law, about fifteen concerning international politics and relations, a half dozen on oriental philosophy, four on religion, and around thirty on a variety of other philosophical subjects.
Series III contains RESEARCH MATERIAL. Filling four boxes, the material consists primarily of newspaper clippings covering the years 1951-1956 organized mostly by country or region but occasionally by subjects. They generally reflect Northrop's interest in international relations and foreign policy.
The largest series in the Northrop Papers is WRITINGS OF OTHERS, housed in Boxes 22-38. It consists of articles and books given to Northrop by other scholars covering a wide variety of philosophical subjects. Many articles bear inscriptions by the authors.
PERSONAL PAPERS, Series V, are contained in Boxes 41-46. Correspondence, primarily consisting of letters sent to Christine Johnston Northrop, is found in folders 923-33. The earliest letters date from the World War I period, when she was serving in France under the auspices of the National War Council of the International Committee of the Young Men's Christian Associations, and were written by male admirers and female friends. The collection contains just seven letters from Filmer Northrop to Christine written in 1938 and 1939. Folder 928 contains a series of January 1940 congratulatory letters and telegrams upon the occasion of Northrop's selection as Master of Silliman College. The series also includes awards, journals and diaries, photographs, and reviews of seven Northrop books. Material in folders 979-83 provides minimal documentation of Northrop's long Yale career and three files, 981-83, concern his Silliman College years. Box 45 is filled with 3 X 5 cards listing books in the library of F.S.C. Northrop and also bibliography cards. Box 46, folders, 986-95, contains oversize materials and includes degrees awarded Northrop and photographs.
The Filmer Stuart Cuckow Northrop Papers provide a great deal of useful information about the professional career and philosophical interests of Northrop, but they provide little documentation of his personal life and relatively little of his forty year teaching career at Yale. Folders 981-83 give some information about his Silliman College years and there is a May 2, 1970 letter to President Kingman Brewster, folder 25, in which Northrop criticizes Brewster for his widely publicized statement concerning the Black Panther trial. In addition, the papers include letters from such well known philosophers and scientists as Teilhard de Chardin, Benedetto Croce, Curt J. Ducasse, Albert Einstein, Sidney Hook, Arthur O. Lovejoy, George Santayana, and Alfred North Whitehead.
Biographical / Historical
Filmer Stuart Cuckow Northrop (1893-1992) was a philosopher, college professor, and author. A member of the Yale faculty, 1923-1962, in the Department of Philosophy and School of Law, he wrote eight major books, including Science and First Principles (1931) and The Meeting of East and West (1946).
1893 born November 27
1915 A.B., Beloit College
1915-1916 social work in New York City
1917-1919 U.S. Army
1919 A.M. in Economics, Yale University
1919 August 6 married Christine Johnston
1919-1920 educational secretary International Committee YMCA in Hong Kong
1922 A.M. in Philosophy, Harvard University
1923-1926 Instructor in Philosophy, Yale University
1924 Ph.D. in Philosophy of Science, Harvard University
1926-1929 Assistant Professor of Philosophy, Yale University
1929-1932 Associate Professor of Philosophy, Yale University
1931 published Science and First Principles
1932-1947 Professor of Philosophy, Yale University
1940-1947 Master of Silliman College
1946 published The Meeting of East and West, An Inquiry Concerning World Understanding
1947 published The Logic of the Sciences and Humanitie s
1947-1962 Sterling Professor of Philosophy and Law, Yale University
1952 published The Taming of the Nations, A Study of the Cultural Bases of International Society
1953 edited Alfred North Whitehead: An Anthology
1954 published European Union and United States Foreign Policy: A Study in Sociological Jurisprudence
1959 published The Complexity of Legal and Ethical Experience
1960 published Philosophical Anthropology and Practical Politics
1962 published Man, Nature and God; A Quest for Life's Meaning
1962 Sterling Professor of Philosophy and Law emeritus
1969 death of Christine Johnston Northrop
1969 married Marjorie Carey
Law -- Philosophy; Hindu philosophy; Philosophy, Modern -- 20th Century; Philosophy, Asian; Philosophy; Religions; Science -- Philosophy; United States -- Foreign relations -- 1945-1953; Diaries; Philosophers; United States -- Foreign relations -- 1945-1989; Moore, Charles Alexander, 1901-1967; Northrop, Christine Johnston, d. 1969; Oliver, Horace G.; Yale University -- Faculty; Silliman College (Yale University)
- PROFESSIONAL PAPERS, 1916-1976; Series I; 5 linear feet (11 boxes)
  Scope and Contents
  PROFESSIONAL PAPERS are divided into two sections. Subject Files are found in Boxes 1-8. The files contain correspondence, reports, and other papers pertaining to Northrop's varied philosophical interests. All material is arranged in a single alphabetical listing by person and subject. Within each folder everything is arranged in chronological order. People and subjects are individually listed provided the file contains five or more items to, from, or about that person or subject. Others are filed alphabetically with the first letter of the surname in "Letter" general. Folders containing ten or more items are marked with an asterisk (*).
  The second section, Notes and Lectures, is housed in Boxes 9-11. notes and lectures are chronologically and then alphabetically arranged. Undated materials are placed last, in folders 267-82.
  - Subject Files
    - "A" general, 1945-1972 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Academy of Human Rights, 1953-1954 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - American Association for the Advancement of Science (*), 1945-1947 (Box 1, Folder 3-5)
    - American Friends of the Middle East, Inc., 1952-1954 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - American Friends Service Committee (*), 1947-1948, undated (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - American Philosophical Association (*), 1940-1941 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - American Philosophical Association: Krusé, Cornelius (*), 1939-1957 (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - American Philosophical Association: Publications Committee (*), 1940-1944 (Box 1, Folder 10-11)
    - American Political Science Association, 1953 (Box 1, Folder 12)
    - Anderle, Othmar, 1953-1961 (Box 1, Folder 13)
    - Association for the Study of European Problems, 1965-1968 (Box 1, Folder 14)
    - Ault, Bromwell, 1947, 1949 (Box 1, Folder 15)
    - Australian trip (*), 1948-1949 (Box 1, Folder 16-21)
    - Austrian conference (*), 1962 (Box 1, Folder 22-23)
    - "B" general, 1931-1974, undated (Box 1, Folder 24-25)
    - Banaras Hindu University, 1954-1955 (Box 1, Folder 26)
    - Bateson, Gregory, 1940, 1943 (Box 1, Folder 27)
    - Bird, Remsen D. (*), 1952-1954 (Box 1, Folder 28)
    - Birker, Lindsay, 1943-1952, undated (Box 1, Folder 29)
    - Brainerd, Charles J., 1974 (Box 2, Folder 30)
    - Breydert, Frederick M., 1954 (Box 2, Folder 31)
    - British Broadcasting Corporation (*), 1947-1948 (Box 2, Folder 32)
    - Brown, Guy Burniston, 1948-1971 (Box 2, Folder 33)
    - Buesst, Tristan N.M., 1951-1970 (Box 2, Folder 34)
      General note
      See also: box 1, folders 19-21
    - "C" general, 1946-1973 (Box 1, Folder 35-37)
    - Callahan, Father Ronan, 1953-1954 (Box 1, Folder 38)
    - Campbell, C.G., 1943-1953 (Box 1, Folder 39)
    - Carlin, Jerome E., 1954-1956 (Box 1, Folder 40)
    - Center for the Study of Moral Order, 1972 (Box 1, Folder 41)
    - Chang, H.H., 1953 (Box 1, Folder 42)
    - Chatterji, Satischandra K., 1951-1952 (Box 1, Folder 43)
    - Chiang Monlin, 1952-1953 (Box 1, Folder 44)
    - Chiang Yee (*), 1947-1949 (Box 1, Folder 45)
    - Clark, Charles E., 1947-1952 (Box 1, Folder 46)
    - Cohen, Robert S., 1949, 1951, undated (Box 1, Folder 47)
    - Colloquium on Islamic Culture (*), 1953 (Box 1, Folder 48)
    - Columbia Broadcasting System (*), 1945-1948 (Box 1, Folder 49)
    - Committee for a Free Asia, Inc., 1952 (Box 1, Folder 50)
    - Conference on Science and Human Responsibility, 1957 (Box 1, Folder 51)
    - Conger, George P., 1940-1950 (Box 1, Folder 52)
    - Coomaraswamy, Ananda K. (*), 1943-1946 (Box 1, Folder 53)
    - "D" general, 1941-1974 (Box 1, Folder 54)
    - de Laguna, Grace, 1941-1946 (Box 1, Folder 55)
    - Dodge, Bayard, 1954 (Box 1, Folder 56)
      See also: box 1, folder 48
    - Donaldson, John, 1947 (Box 1, Folder 57)
    - Donnelly, Richard C., 1948-1949 (Box 1, Folder 58)
    - Douglass, Paul, 1971 (Box 1, Folder 59)
    - Dyason, Edward C.
      See: box 1, folders 19-21
    - "E" general, 1930-1968, n.d (Box 1, Folder 60)
    - East-West Philosophers' Conference
      See: box 5, folders 156-158
    - Ebin, Alexander, 1951, undated (Box 1, Folder 61)
    - Einstein, Albert (*), 1927-1953 (Box 1, Folder 62)
    - Estey, J.A., 1947-1948 (Box 1, Folder 63)
    - "F" general, 1941-1965, undated (Box 1, Folder 64)
    - Fernandez, Justina, 1943-1947 (Box 1, Folder 65)
    - Fischer, Hugo, 1952 (Box 1, Folder 66)
    - Flewelling, Ralph Tyler, 1946-1947 (Box 3, Folder 67)
    - Fonseca, J. Simoes de (*), 1970-1975 (Box 3, Folder 68)
    - Frank, Lawrence K. (*), 1939-1948 (Box 3, Folder 69)
    - Fung, Yu-lan, 1947-1949 (Box 3, Folder 70)
    - Fyzee, Asaf Ali Asghar (*), 1951-1953, undated (Box 3, Folder 71)
    - "G" general, 1946-1971, undated (Box 3, Folder 72-73)
    - Ganguli, Jatindra Mohan, 1974-1976 (Box 3, Folder 74)
    - German trip (*), 1952-1953 (Box 3, Folder 75)
    - Goodridge, Elinor, 1947 (Box 3, Folder 76)
    - Gourevitch, Boris, 1957 (Box 3, Folder 77)
    - Governor's School of North Carolina, 1955 (Box 3, Folder 78)
    - Greene, Theodore M. (*), 1940-1951 (Box 3, Folder 79)
    - Grinnell, Robert, 1946-1950 (Box 3, Folder 80)
    - Growth, 1940-1944 (Box 3, Folder 81)
    - Grunbaum, Adolph (*), 1951-1959 (Box 3, Folder 82)
    - Guerra Perez-Carral, Francisco, 1944-1947 (Box 3, Folder 83)
    - Gullette, George A., 1955 (Box 3, Folder 84)
    - "H" general, 1925-1970 (Box 3, Folder 85-87)
    - Hall, Jerome, 1948-1951 (Box 3, Folder 88)
    - Harper & Brothers, 1949, 1952 (Box 3, Folder 89)
    - Hasan, Mumtaz, 1951 (Box 3, Folder 90)
    - Hawaii, University of: East-West Philosophers' Conference, 1948-1949 (Box 3, Folder 91)
    - Heisenberg, Werner Karl, 1958, 1974 (Box 3, Folder 92)
    - Hendel, Charles W., 1940-1943 (Box 3, Folder 93)
    - Hook, Sidney (*), 1953-1958 (Box 3, Folder 94)
    - Hooker, M.B., 1960-1966 (Box 3, Folder 95)
    - Hopson, Dan, Jr. (*), 1954-1956 (Box 4, Folder 96)
    - Hovland, C.W., 1952 (Box 4, Folder 97)
    - Hughes, E.R. (*), 1946-1950 (Box 4, Folder 98)
    - Hume, Edward H. (*), 1942-1948 (Box 4, Folder 99)
    - Hunt, Richard B., 1949-1955 (Box 4, Folder 100)
    - Hunt, Richard C. (Box 4, Folder 100)
    - "I" general, 1947, 1972 (Box 4, Folder 101)
    - Indian Philosophical Congress (*), 1950-1954 (Box 4, Folder 102)
    - Industrial Research Institute, Inc., 1952 (Box 4, Folder 103)
    - Infantry Journal, 1950 (Box 4, Folder 104)
    - International Conference on Asian Problems, 1953-1954 (Box 4, Folder 105)
    - The Igbal Society, 1951-1953, undated (Box 4, Folder 106)
    - "J" general, 1954-1970 (Box 4, Folder 107)
    - Jones, Howard Humford, 1946, 1948 (Box 4, Folder 108)
    - "K" general, 1947-1973, undated (Box 4, Folder 109)
    - Karim, F.A., 1952, undated (Box 4, Folder 110)
    - Kilmer, William, 1970, 1974, undated (Box 4, Folder 111)
    - Kluckholm, Clyde (*), 1948-1952 (Box 4, Folder 112)
    - Krusé, Cornelius
      See: box 1, folder 9
    - "L" general, 1936-1970, undated (Box 4, Folder 113)
    - Lanier, Emilio Aquinaldo, 1948-1953 (Box 4, Folder 114)
    - Law school: lectures and outside meetings (*), 1953-1961 (Box 4, Folder 115-116)
    - Leckie, George, 1934-1936 (Box 4, Folder 117)
    - Lectures and outside meetings (*), 1953-1963 (Box 4, Folder 118-120)
    - Lectures: U.S. and Canadian War Colleges (*), 1948-1961 (Box 4, Folder 121-122)
    - Leonard, W.N., 1951-1952 (Box 4, Folder 123)
    - Levinson, Marshall M. (*), 1952-1953 (Box 4, Folder 124)
    - Lewis, H. Michael (*), 1968-1972 (Box 4, Folder 125)
    - Lewis, Jacqueline (Box 4, Folder 125)
    - Library of Living Philosophers (*), 1941-1951 (Box 4, Folder 126)
    - Life (*), 1951-1952 (Box 4, Folder 127)
    - Lindsay, Lord of Birker, 1946-1951 (Box 4, Folder 128)
    - Lippmann, Walter, 1953-1954 (Box 4, Folder 129)
    - Lobenstine, Edwin C. (*), 1946-1947 (Box 5, Folder 130)
    - Lovejoy, Arthur O. (*), 1940-1950 (Box 5, Folder 131)
    - Lowe, Victor (*), 1948-1969 (Box 5, Folder 132)
    - "M" general, 1924-1974 (Box 5, Folder 133-134)
    - MacClamroch, James G.W., 1953-1954 (Box 5, Folder 135)
    - The Macmillan Company (*), 1940-1971 (Box 5, Folder 136-138)
    - The Macmillan Company: Whitehead anthology (*), 1946-1955 (Box 5, Folder 139-140)
    - McCulloch, Warren S. (*), 1946-1965 (Box 5, Folder 141-142)
    - Macy, Josiah, Jr. Foundation (*), 1946-1954 (Box 5, Folder 143)
      See also: box 3, folder 69
    - Mandelbaum, Maurice
      See: box 1, folder 8
    - Maquet, Jacques J. (*), 1948-1949 (Box 5, Folder 144)
    - Massuh, Victor, 1954-1956 (Box 5, Folder 145)
    - Métraux, Guy S., 1964-1965 (Box 5, Folder 146)
    - Mexican embassy: cultural mission (*), 1943-1952, undated (Box 5, Folder 147-149)
    - Mexico: Interamerican Congress of Philosophy (*), 1949 (Box 5, Folder 150)
    - Moore, Charles A. (*), 1940-1958 March (Box 5, Folder 151-156)
    - Moore, Charles A., 1958 April-1959 (Box 6, Folder 157-158)
    - Moore, Underhill, 1940-1949 (Box 6, Folder 159)
    - Morgenstern, Oskar, 1941-1950 (Box 6, Folder 160)
    - Morocco conference (*), 1957-1958 (Box 6, Folder 161)
    - Motwani, Kewal, 1947-1969 (Box 6, Folder 162)
    - "N" general, 1931-1972 (Box 6, Folder 163)
    - New Zealand: Treaty of Waitangi facsimiles, 1960 (Box 6, Folder 164)
    - Nicoll, Allardyce, 1944-1947 (Box 6, Folder 165)
    - Nikam, N.A.
      See: box 4, folder 102
    - Nikhilananda, Swami, 1947-1954 (Box 6, Folder 166)
    - "O" general, 1950-1972 (Box 6, Folder 167)
    - Ohsava, I.J.G., 1948-1949 (Box 6, Folder 168)
    - Olds, Glenn A., 1971-1972 (Box 6, Folder 169)
    - Oliver, Horace G., Jr. (*), 1970-1976 (Box 6, Folder 170-175)
    - "P" general, 1931-1971, undated (Box 6, Folder 176)
    - Paton, H. J. (philosopher), 1959-1960 (Box 6, Folder 177)
    - Peverelli, Bruno de (*), 1952-1954, undated (Box 6, Folder 178)
    - Peverelli, Piero de (*), 1949-1968 (Box 6, Folder 179)
    - Pierson, John H.G., 1955-1971 (Box 6, Folder 180)
    - Planck, Friedrich, 1957-1958 (Box 7, Folder 181)
    - Princeton University, 1946-1947 (Box 7, Folder 182)
    - "Q" general, 1946, 1974 (Box 7, Folder 183)
    - "R" general, 1932-1974, undated (Box 7, Folder 184)
    - Rathbone, Rodion, 1960-1961 (Box 7, Folder 185)
    - Ray, Rudolph (*), 1957-1970, undated (Box 7, Folder 186)
    - Ray, Joyce (Box 7, Folder 186)
    - Reck, Andrew J., 1960 (Box 7, Folder 187)
    - Reston, James B., 1953-1954 (Box 7, Folder 188)
    - Reyes, Alfonso (*), 1943-1952 (Box 7, Folder 189)
    - Rodriguez, Guillermo, 1949-1950 (Box 7, Folder 190)
    - Romero, Francisco, 1944-1954 (Box 7, Folder 191)
    - "S" general, 1940-1974, undated (Box 7, Folder 192)
    - Sambursky, S., 1962-1971 (Box 7, Folder 193)
    - Schleicher, Carl, 1972 (Box 7, Folder 194)
    - SEATO Round Table (*), 1956-1958 (Box 7, Folder 195-200)
    - Smith, Joseph C. (*), 1965-1970 (Box 7, Folder 201)
    - Spratt, John (*), 1970-1972, undated (Box 8, Folder 202)
    - State, Department of (*), 1944-1961 (Box 8, Folder 203-206)
    - Student paper: Benitez, Clotilde "Roman Influence in the Family Law of Puerto Rico with Special Reference to Women and Wills", 1961 (Box 8, Folder 207)
    - Student paper: Muller-Rafford "Comparative Review of the Treatment of the Unawareness of the Unlawfulness", Circa1960-1962 (Box 8, Folder 208)
    - Student paper: Penegar, Kenneth Lawing "Sir Robert Filmer, Patriarchalism, and the South's Living Law", 1962 (Box 8, Folder 209)
    - "T" general, 1941-1974 (Box 8, Folder 210)
    - Tartar, Vance, 1948-1972 (Box 8, Folder 211)
    - Thayer, Lee (*), 1970-1972 (Box 8, Folder 212)
    - Tollett, Kenneth S., 1961-1969 (Box 8, Folder 213)
    - "U" general, 1952 (Box 8, Folder 214)
    - "V" general, 1947-1971 (Box 8, Folder 215)
    - "W" general, 1931-1972, undated (Box 8, Folder 216)
    - Wahl, Jean, 1943 (Box 8, Folder 217)
    - Whitehead, Alfred North, 1923-1946 (Box 8, Folder 218)
    - Win, Khin Maung (*), 1959-1962 (Box 8, Folder 219)
    - "Y" general, 1949-1972, undated (Box 8, Folder 220)
    - Yntema, Hessel E., 1952 (Box 8, Folder 221)
    - "Z" general, 1948-1971, undated (Box 8, Folder 222)
    - Unidentified, 1935-1971, undated (Box 8, Folder 223)
  - Notes and Lectures
    - Notes: Greek philosophy, with Charles Bakewell, 1916 (Box 9, Folder 224)
    - Notes: economics, 1919 (Box 9, Folder 225)
    - Notes: Kant, 1920-1922 (Box 9, Folder 226-227)
    - Notes: philosophy lectures at Harvard, 1921-1923 (Box 9, Folder 228)
    - Notes: ancient and modern philosophy, [pre-1923?] (Box 9, Folder 229)
    - Notes: Husserl on the history of philosophy, [pre-1923?] (Box 9, Folder 230)
    - Notes: metaphysics, [pre-1923?] (Box 9, Folder 231)
    - Notes: philosophy and evolution, [pre-1923?] (Box 9, Folder 232)
    - Notes: philosophy, miscellaneous, [pre-1923?] (Box 9, Folder 233)
    - Notes: psychology, [pre-1923?] (Box 9, Folder 234)
    - Notes: Ward James, [pre-1923?] (Box 9, Folder 235)
    - Notes: philosophy of science, 1922-1923 (Box 9, Folder 236)
    - Lectures: class materials and outlines, 1922-1926, undated (Box 9, Folder 237)
    - Notes: on Bayliss' Principles of General Physiology, [ca.1924] (Box 9, Folder 238)
    - Lectures: philosophy, [ca.1926] (Box 9, Folder 239-241)
    - Lectures: Pike lecture, 1927 (Box 9, Folder 242)
    - Notes: Locke, Berkeley and Hume, [1927?] (Box 9, Folder 243)
    - Notes: on G.P. Gooch, [ca.1930] (Box 9, Folder 244)
    - Lectures: abstract for "Logic and Science", 1935 (Box 10, Folder 245)
    - Lectures: abstracts for "Philosophy of Science", 1935-1937 (Box 10, Folder 246-247)
    - Notes: meeting with Alexander von Wirthenan, 1943 (Box 10, Folder 248)
    - Notes: Conference on Teleological Mechanisms, 1947 (Box 10, Folder 249)
    - Notes: Conference with Professor Karl Friedrich, 1949 (Box 10, Folder 250)
    - Notes: East-West Philosophers Conference, 1949 (Box 10, Folder 251)
    - Notes: on European politics, [ca.1952] (Box 10, Folder 252)